Register to the Paul Hindemith Collection
Yale University Music Library
- MISCELLANEOUS MATERIALS, 1940-1988; Series X; 3.5' (8 boxes)
  - Paul Hindemith Collection Summary (Box 27, Folder 392)
    - Microfilm Reel No. 2 Index comprising original manuscripts & photocopies, 1988
    - Papers in the Osborn Collection, Beinecke Library, 1988
    - Official Index of the Collection, 1982
    - Curator's report, 1973
  - Gesamtausgabe announcements & correspondence with the Foundation (Box 27, Folder 393)
  - Gesamtausgabe Stylebook, 1971-1972 (Box 27, Folder 394)
  - D. Neumeyer: texts/corrections for III, 7 (Box 27, Folder 395)
    - Concerto for Trumpet, Bassoon & Strings
    - Concerto for Woodwinds, Harp, & Orchestra
  - D. Neumeyer: working notes for III, 7 (Box 27, Folder 396)
  - Paul Hindemith Collection Miscellaneous (Box 27, Folder 397)
  - Collection Expenses, 1974 (Box 28, Folder 398)
  - Paul Hindemith als Dirigent und Soloist im Rundfunk (Deutsches Rundfunkarchiv) A list of recorded and live performances from Germany, Denmark, Austria, Italy, Switzerland, Sweden, et al., 1965 (Box 28, Folder 399)
  - George Lam letters re: organization of the Paul Hindemith Collection, 1964 (Box 28, Folder 400)
  - Paul Hindemith Bibliography by Eliz. Westphal, et. al., 1957 (Box 28, Folder 401)
  - [Untitled] (Box 28, Folder 402)
    - Collection Newsletter, 1972-1973
    - University of Kentucky Festival - programs, 1973
    - Ohio State University Festival, 1973
  - L'Ecole Hindemith programs, brochures (Box 28, Folder 403)
  - Mailing List, 1973-1974 (Box 28, Folder 404)
  - [Untitled] (Box 28, Folder 405)
    - Permission forms - for copies, requests, etc.
    - Correspondence relating to assembling the Collection, arranged alphabetically
  - A. Collection Correspondence (Box 29, Folder 406)
  - B. Collection Correspondence, 1963-1978 (Box 29, Folder 407)
  - B. Collection Correspondence, 1979-1992 (Box 29, Folder 408)
  - C. Collection Correspondence (Box 29, Folder 409)
  - D. Collection Correspondence (Box 29, Folder 410)
  - E. Collection Correspondence (Box 29, Folder 411)
  - F. Collection Correspondence (Box 29, Folder 412)
  - G. Collection Correspondence (Box 29, Folder 413)
  - H. Collection Correspondence (Box 29, Folder 414)
  - I/J. Collection Correspondence (Box 29, Folder 415)
  - K. Collection Correspondence (Box 29, Folder 416)
  - L. Collection Correspondence (Box 29, Folder 417)
  - M. Collection Correspondence (Box 29, Folder 418)
  - N. Collection Correspondence (Box 29, Folder 419)
  - O/P/Q. Collection Correspondence (Box 30, Folder 420)
  - R. Collection Correspondence (Box 30, Folder 421)
  - S. Collection Correspondence + Straumann letters re: Gertrud Hindemith's death (Box 30, Folder 422)
  - T/U/V. Collection Correspondence (Box 30, Folder 423)
  - W/X/Y/Z. Collection Correspondence (Box 30, Folder 424)
- HOLOGRAPH MATERIALS, 1938-1953; Series XI; 12' (12 boxes)
  The 16 musical holographs in the Yale University Hindemith Collection include songs for children and professionals, concertos, the Requiem, sketches for The Four Temperaments, Organ Sonata No. 3, and a 5-part canon. Two songs (Folders 431 & 436) were composed for Carl Lohmann, Secretary of Yale University from the mid-1940s to the early 1950s. Lohmann possessed a fine singing voice and could read music at sight. This material is unknown outside a small circle of New Haven residents.
  The score of "Lilacs" was presented to the collection by Gertrud Hindemith after the composer's death.
  Oscar Cox, the poet who provided the texts to Hindemith's songs "Image" and "Beauty Touch Me," was a lawyer in Washington, D. C. Cox guided through Congress the release of Hindemith's royalties which had accrued in the office of the U. S. Alien Property Custodian throughout World War II and afterwards.
  - MUSIC, A
    - Songs for children, 1938 (Box 31, Folder 425)
      Reel 2/501-537
      - [Songs for children, selections] Songs by Paul Hindemith.
        1 score (31 p. ); 19 x 26 cm. Holograph, in ink and pencil.
        - Contains songs nos. 3-9 in a Schirmer's Manuscript Music Book, stamped throughout: Silver, Burdett & Company.
        - On cover: we paid $200.00 March 23, 1938 for songs in this book (7) and "The Spider's Web" and "Romance." Mounts made for 9 Songs.
        - Also on cover: Miss Harrison, Silver, Burdett Co., 45 East 17th St.
        - Typescripts of poems pasted in at end of each song.
        - Contents: Rain --
      - [Songs for children. Spider's web] The Spider's Web.
        1 score (2 p. ); 27 x 34 cm. Holograph, in ink.
        - On title page in black pencil: Lieber Mr. Bartholomew, wenn Ihnen diese Lieder recht sind, können Sie mehr (?) einege davon haben. Dann hätte ich mehr im einege Texte für Auswahl gebeten.
        - Also on title page: Bartholomew in red pencil.
        - At end in pencil: Stimmung mit oder ohne Klavier.
      - [Songs for children. Romance] Romance.
        - At end in pencil: 1 Stimmung ohne Klavier; 2 Stimmung ohne Klavier; 1 Stimmung mit Klavier; 2 Stimmung mit Klavier.
    - [Sonatas, organ, no. 3] Sonate für Orgel nach alten Volkslieder / Paul Hindemith -- Buffalo, 1940 (Box 31, Folder 426)
      1 score (17 p.); 35 cm. Holograph, in ink. Reel 2/461-477.
      - On title page: For Frank Bozyan in friendship!
      - At end of 1st and 3rd movement: Buffalo 5. Juni 40.
      - At end of 2nd movement: Buffalo 25 Mai 1940.
      - On inside of title page: I. Ach Gott, wenn sollt ich's Klagen; II. Wach auf, mein Herz; III. So wünsch ich ihr [ein gute Nacht].
      - Annotations, in pencil, by Frank Bozyan.
      - With presentation letter to F. Bozyan, dated Dec. 24, 1945.
      - Bequest of Prof. Frank Bozyan.
    - [Four temperaments (sketches)] Theme and four Variations (according to the four Temperaments) for String Orchestra and Piano / Paul Hindemith -- New Haven, Conn., Oct 1940 (Box 31, Folder 427)
      40 p. of music; 18 x 14 cm. Holograph, in pencil. Reel 2/419-460.
      - Sketches for ballet.
      - On front orange binding: BALANCHINE.
      - On flyleaf: Für Grummans mit herzlichen Dank für zahlreiche Freundlichkeiten und für Erinnerung am Hindemiths, New Haven Conn 1941 Mar.
      - With note: Original SketchBook. The book itself made by Mr. Hindemith. Written for Balanchine whose name appears (faded) on orange binding.
      - Gift of Ellsworth Grumman.
    - [Canon, voices (5)] Exercise in strict composition (with fifth parallels, exceptionally permitted), 1940 (Box 31, Folder 428)
      1 score (1 p.); 24 cm. Holograph, in ink. Reel 2/563-564.
      - On title page: Nov. 29th 1940 New Haven Conn A birthday canon for Richard Donovan.
      - Gift of Professor Donovan.
    - [Belle dame sans merci] La belle dame sans merci für Soprano und Klavier / Paul Hindemith, 1942 (Box 31, Folder 429)
      1 score (14 p.); 31 cm. Holograph, in ink. Reel 2/478-492.
      - On title page: To Oscar Cox with many thanks July 1951
      - At end: New Haven, Conn 10.9.42
      - Text by John Keats.
      - With presentation letter from Paul Hindemith.
      - Gift of Oscar Cox.
    - [Sing on there in the swamp] Sing on there in the swamp / Paul Hindemith, 1943 (Box 31, Folder 430)
      1 score (4 p.); 32 cm. Holograph, in ink. Reel 2/163-168.
      - For voice and piano.
      - On title page: Dear Judge Hincks, we would be glad if you would accept this musical token of gratitude for your kindness.
      - Gertrude and Paul Hindemith May 1946
      - At end: New Haven 8. Nov. 43.
      - Text by Walt Whitman.
      - Includes a letter from Judge Carroll Clark Hincks to Ellsworth Grumman - Mar 11 autograph letter signed.
      - Gift of Ellsworth Grumman.
    - [Recitativo, aria ranatica] Recitativo e aria ranatica / Paul Hindemith, 1944 (Box 31, Folder 431)
      1 score (8 p.); 32 cm. Holograph, in ink. Reel 2/538-551.
      - On title page: Bass and Piano; written for Carl A. Lohmann
      - At end: Jonathan Edwards [College] April 6th, 1944
      - Texts by Charles Dickens and Encyclopaedia Britannica.
      - Printed program: Grand gala gas-light concert of Morceaux de Salon... Jonathan Edwards College [16 April 1944]. Includes first performance of the above composition, listed as: The Expiring Frog: recitative e aria ranatica.
      - With autograph letter signed presentation letter to Carl Lohmann, undated [April 1944?].
      - Typed letter signed presentation letter from C. Lohmann to B. Shepard [23 January 1957).
      - Also program of 7 November 1964 containing a full account of its origins.
      - Gift of Carl Lohmann.
    - [When lilacs last in the door-yard bloom'd] When lilacs last in the door-yard bloom'd a requiem for those we love / Paul Hindemith, 1946 (Box 32, Folder 432)
      1 score (163 p.); 34 cm. Holograph, in ink. Reel 2/1-162.
      - Manuscript pasted on single pages, unbound.
      - On title page: Alto Solo -- Baritone Solo -- Mixed Chorus; Orchestra:
        Piccolo
        Flute
        Oboe
        English Horn
        Clarinet in B-flat
        Bass Clarinet
        Bassoon
        Contra Bassoon
        3 Horns in F
        2 Trumpets in B-flat
        2 Trombones
        Tuba
        Timpani (3)
        Percussion (3 players)
        Organ
        Army bugle (backstage)
        Strings
      - On lst page of music: Copyright, 1946, by Associated Music Publishers, Inc., New York
      - At end: The End. New Haven, Conn. April 20th, 1946
      - Text by Walt Whitman.
      - Gift of Gertrud Hindemith.
    - [Concertos, clarinet, orchestra] Concerto for clarinet and orchestra / Paul Hindemith, 1947 (Box 31A, Folder 433)
      1 score (88 p.); 35 cm. Holograph, in ink. Reel 2/292-379.
      - On title page: written for Benny Goodman
      - At end: Switzerland New Haven, Conn. Summer 1947
      - On fly leaf: For Louise and Oscar Cox in gratitude for their unique friendship. Gertrude Hindemith Christmas 1965
      - Includes photo of Paul Hindemith, inscribed "In his name" by Gertrud Hindemith.
      - Gift of Oscar Cox.
    - [Concertos, horn, orchestra] Concerto for horn and orchestra / Paul Hindemith, 1949 (Box 31A, Folder 434)
      1 score (39 p.); 34 cm. Holograph, in ink. Reel 2/380-418.
      - On title page: To Oscar with love. Paul Hindemith 1955
      - At end: Sierre 18.III.49
      - Gift of Oscar Cox.
    - [Concertos, trumpet, bassoon, string orchestra (sketches)] Concerto for trumpet, bassoon and strings / Paul Hindemith -- New Haven, Conn., 1949 (Box 32, Folder 435)
      1 score (52 p.); 16 x 22 cm. Holograph, in pencil. Reel 2/237-291.
      - Score is unbound; composer cut manuscript pages. They are not in sequence.
      - Gift of the composer, 1953.
    - [Concertos, trumpet, bassoon, string orchesta] Konzert für Trompete, Fagott, und Streich orchester = Concerto for trumpet, bassoon, and string orchestra / Paul Hindemith, 1949 (Box 32, Folder 435)
      1 score (48 p.); 34 cm. Holograph, in ink. Reel 2/169-236.
      - At end of 2nd movement: New Haven, Conn. Sept. 30th, 1949
      - 7 parts (2 p. each); 32 cm.
      - Commissioned by the Connecticut Academy of Arts & Sciences for their Sesquicentennial
      - Celebration in 1949.
      - Gift of the composer, 1953.
    - [Cal, the lad of Ohio's anniversary song] Cal, the lad of Ohio's anniversary song / Paul Hindemith, 1951 (Box 31A, Folder 436)
      1 score (2 p. ) 32 cm. Holograph, in pencil. (see also Box 41 of the Lohmann murals)
      - On title page: for our good friends, the Lohmanns. The Hindemiths.
      - With: Holograph, in ink (half-page); 16 x 24 cm. comprising melody and bass, with Refrain text laid in + pencil corrections.
      - Text by Francis W. Bronson, editor of Yale Alumni Magazine, on 12 typed cards, each containing 8-lines.
      - 2 p. letter Gertrud Hindemith-C. Lohmann 24 May 1953.
      - 2 p. letter John Lohmann-C. Moretto 7/81.
      - Drawings / Paul Hindemith -- 1951. Holograph, in pencil, both sides; 21 x 30cm. on which are 12 images of Carl Lohmann.
      - Gift of John Lohmann, 1981?.
    - [Songs (1955). Image] Image, for soprano (or tenor) and piano / Paul Hindemith (Box 31A, Folder 437)
      1 vocal score (3 p.); 34 cm. Holograph, in ink. Reel 2/493-496.
      - On title page: To Oscar and Louise
      - At end: Blonay 29. Jan. 1955
      - Text by Oscar Cox.
      - Typescript of poem pasted on title page
      - Gift of Oscar Cox.
    - [Songs (1955). Beauty touch me] Beauty touch me, for soprano (or tenor) and piano / Paul Hindemith (Box 31A, Folder 437)
      1 vocal score (3 p.); 34 cm. Hologaph, in ink. Reel 2/497-500.
      - On title page: To Oscar and Louise
      - At end: Blonay 30. Jan 1955
      - Text by Oscar Cox.
      - Typescript of poem pasted on title page
      - Gift of Oscar Cox.
  - OTHER ITEMS, B
    - [Panorama-Kasten/peep show instructions], undated (Box 31A, Folder 438)
      - Instruction sheet, in pencil by unknown German hand.
      - Includes Paul Hindemith's holograph pencil notes in English.
    - [Traditional harmony, part 2] Traditional Harmony, book 2., 1948 (Box 31A, Folder 439)
      Typescript (43 p.) with 36 p. of mimeographed music manuscript. not in Paul Hindemith's hand; 28 cm. Holograph in red ink.
      - Includes corrections by Paul Hindemith (5 p.; 28 cm. ). Each correction is numbered
    - [Traditional harmony, part 2] Traditional Harmony, book 2. [Book of Musical Examples], 1948 (Box 31A, Folder 439)
      Holograph, in ink, hand bound; 19 x 22 cm. Chapters IX to XV, on one side of paper only, with many annotations, and typescript texts of songs and choral pieces stapled in.
      - Published copy of German edition with corrections marked in red by Paul Hindemith. (Schott, 1949)
      - Announcement of American edition from AMP.
      - Gift of Mrs. Kurt Stone.
    - MICROFILMS
      - [Untitled] (Box 33)
        - Craft of Musical Composition III - Chapters 12-16 in English; Chapters 16-20 in German - negative & positive
        - Paul Hindemith Music Manuscripts - master negative & positive
        - Paul Hindemith Correspondence - master negative & positive
      - 1945-1953 (Box 34, Folder a.)
        - Boatwright Collection 300-BR
        - Collegium Musicum inventory
        - Inventory of Boatwright & Lam Collections
        - Programs & Music
        - Commemoratio Brevis
        - Zwanzigste Übung
        - Exercises for Students of Harmony, 1942
        - Three-Part Writing, Chapters 15-16, 1942
        - Elementary Training for Musicians, published draft, 1945
        - Paul Hindemith: Sonata for Two Pianos - sketches - negative, 1944
    - MISCELLANEOUS
      - Two handpainted Easter eggs by Paul Hindemith for R. Kirkpatrick, given by him to the collection (Box 34, Folder b.)
      - Paul Hindemith's favorite lead crystal liquer glass from the household of Karl Bauer; given by Phyllis Bauer (Box 34, Folder c.)
      - [Untitled] (Box 35)
        - Handpainted window shade/scroll by Paul Hindemith made for the farewell party at 137 Alden Ave., New Haven, 1953
        - 14 Handpainted Panels on butcher paper in color, each 76.5 x 90.2 cm, sealed in mylar; made for celebration of C. A. Lohmann's retirement as Secretary of the University (see also Photographs & Drawings 20/333), 1953
      - Singing Frog & Lohmann Cartoon; Lohmann Akron to Yale (Box 36)
      - Gardener trimming: Lohmann with eggs & heraldry (Box 37)
      - Cal 25; Mortar boards & shoes (Box 38)
      - Lohmann in bed, dreaming; Lohmann with music box (Box 39)
      - Lohmann as Caesar; Where is Caesar? (Box 40)
      - Four Lohmanns quartet; He is the foam on our ale [music] (Box 41)
      - Lohmann tied up with mannequins behind him; Lohmann as jack-of-all-trades (Box 42)
- OVERSIZE ITEMS, Series XII
  - [Untitled] (Box 43)
    - Poster from Library exhibit, 1964
    - Clef reading exercises, 1964
    - B & W photo by Ernesto Epistola of Paul Hindemith in rehearsal for concert 19 February, 1960
    - Photocopy of Paul Hindemith: Harmonieübungen für Fortgeschrittene, Zweiter Teil der "Aufgaben für Harmonieschuler"- completely handwritten in German + letter from D. Kraehenbuehl, 1948
    - Photocopy of Paul Hindemith: Elementary training for Musicians, completely typed text with C. Rosenthal? notation examples, 1945-46
    - Paul Hindemith's handwritten masters for Collegium concert, 1948
    - Composite mass, 1948
    - Josquin: Miserere, 1948
    - von Bruck/Greiter/Isaac/Senfl 2x/Finck: Ich stund an einem Morgen, 1948
    - Senfl 2x/Heugel 2x/Stoltzer: Entlaubet ist der Walde, 1948
    - Senfl/Isaac: Zwischen Berg und tiefem Tal, 1948
    - Finck/Hofhaimer/Isaac: Greiner, Zanner, 1948
    - Lemlin: Der Gutzgauch auf dem Zaune sass, 1948
    - Jannequin: Le chant des oixeaux, 1948
    - Willaert: Credo, unused, 1948
    - Photocopy of Paul Hindemith: Concerto for Trumpet, Bassoon, and Strings sketches, full score, solo parts in Paul Hindemith autograph; piano reduction in another hand, 1949
- SOUND RECORDINGS, Series XIII
  Sound recordings found in the Paul Hindemith Collection have been transferred to the Yale Library's Historical Sound Recordings Collection.